<NewsML Version="1.2" xmlns="http://iptc.org/std/NewsML/2003-10-10/">
	<NewsEnvelope>
		<TransmissionId>urn:publicid:ap.org:111668</TransmissionId>
		<SentFrom>
			<Party FormalName="The Associated Press" />
		</SentFrom>
		<DateAndTime>20220213T231724</DateAndTime>
		<NewsService FormalName="news" />
	</NewsEnvelope>
	<NewsItem>
		<Identification>
			<NewsIdentifier>
				<ProviderId>www.ap.org</ProviderId>
				<DateId>20220213</DateId>
				<NewsItemId>23bbefcd-5d7c-4664-8db7-133be328a396.1</NewsItemId>
				<RevisionId PreviousRevision="0" Update="N">1</RevisionId>
				<PublicIdentifier>urn:newsml:www.ap.org:20220213:23bbefcd-5d7c-4664-8db7-133be328a396.1:1</PublicIdentifier>
			</NewsIdentifier>
			<Label>
				<LabelType FormalName="StoryNumber" />
				<LabelText>4365900</LabelText>
			</Label>
		</Identification>
		<NewsManagement>
			<NewsItemType FormalName="Video" />
			<FirstCreated>20220213T231724</FirstCreated>
			<ThisRevisionCreated>20220213T231724</ThisRevisionCreated>
			<Status FormalName="Usable" />
		</NewsManagement>
		<NewsComponent Essential="yes" EquivalentsList="yes">
			<Role FormalName="Main" />
			<BasisForChoice>MimeType/@FormalName</BasisForChoice>
			<NewsLines>
				<HeadLine>French conservative Pécresse holds presidential rally</HeadLine>
				<DateLine>13 February 2022 - Paris</DateLine>
				<SlugLine>France Election Pecresse-Pecresse</SlugLine>
			</NewsLines>
			<AdministrativeMetadata />
			<NewsComponent>
				<Role FormalName="Script" />
				<ContentItem>
					<MimeType FormalName="application/xhtml+xml" />
					<DataContent>
						<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
							<div>
								<p></p>
								<p>SHOTLIST:</p>
								<p>RESTRICTION SUMMARY:</p>
								<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p>Paris, France 13 September, 2022</p>
								<p>1. Wide supporters of Valerie Pecresse for President waving French Tri-Colour Flags as they await the candidate's entrance</p>
								<p>2. Tilt up on Valerie Pecresse campaign posters to Young Republicans waving flags at the Pecresse rally</p>
								<p>3. Valerie Pecresse enters the packed venue waving with cameras trailing her </p>
								<p>4. Pan of crowd of supporters holding French flags</p>
								<p>5. Young Republicans chanting (French) "We're going to win, we're going to win."</p>
								<p>6. Pecresse on the screen above the crowd</p>
								<p>7. SOUNDBITE (French) Valerie Pecresse, Presidential candidate of the conservative Les Republicains Party: </p>
								<p>"I want to bring a new hope, one of a new France that we must rebuild together."</p>
								<p>8. Pecresse supporters inside the venue with French flags</p>
								<p>9. A banner by the far-right group Nemesis Collective that reads (French) "Don't be Fooled" with a play on the word "veiled" was quickly pulled down as soon as it went up inside the venue during Pecresse's speech</p>
								<p>10. SOUNDBITE (French) Valerie Pecresse, Presidential candidate of the conservative Les Republicains Party: </p>
								<p>"The extremists are lying to you. Refuse the venom of nostalgia. Don't let anger or fear win. I embody, with you, order in the Republic. They are the disorder. I embody the force of the national unity. They are disunity. Against this extremism, chose a firm and fair hand."</p>
								<p>11. Young Republicains chanting (French) "We are going to win."</p>
								<p>12. SOUNDBITE (French) Valerie Pecresse, Presidential candidate of the conservative Les Republicains Party:</p>
								<p>"Are you ready to charge to victory? I am here. So follow me. Long live the Republic. Long live France."</p>
								<p>13. Zoom out to Pecresse and jubilant crowd</p>
								<p>14. SOUNDBITE (French) Iphigenia Kameni, Pecresse Supporter and Versailles-based Entrepreneur (who had met Pecresse years ago at a Women's symposium she organized):</p>
								<p>"I discovered an authentic woman, contrary to what we see on television, committed and as a woman, I decided to support her candidacy because I feel this is the winning ticket in order to go much further for women."</p>
								<p>15. Cutaway Young Republicains clapping, Louis Ferbus among them</p>
								<p>16. SOUNDBITE (English) Louis Ferbus, Young Republicain, Law Student:</p>
								<p>"We'll be able to have better jobs and they will be easier and she has proposed to get the taxes down so that the companies will be able to employ more people. So yes she can do."</p>
								<p>17. Cutaway young supporters brought on stage by Pecresse</p>
								<p>18. SOUNBITE (French) Etane Regis, Young Republicain, 19 year old University Student:</p>
								<p>"Because the French Republic is also a meritocracy and that's in part why I am supporting Valerie Pecresse, it's because I want to believe in meritocracy, to believe that we can start from the lowest rung on the ladder and rise to reach the highest summits."</p>
								<p>19. Cutaway Pecresse on stage with Les Republicains Party elders</p>
								<p>20. SOUNDBITE (French) Armelle Cassin, Pecresse Supporter/Mayor of Argentonnay in Western France:</p>
								<p>"She embodies the hopes of all French women, she also embodies the hope of France because she knows France and that's something you can't take away from her. She knows where she's going. She knows where she's from and she knows where she is going."</p>
								<p>21. Jubilant crowds inside venue</p>
								<p>STORYLINE: </p>
								<p>A conservative politician vying to become France's first female leader is hoping to boost her declining fortunes in the campaign so far with her first major rally.</p>
								<p>Less than 60 days from the first round of France's presidential election on April 10, Valérie Pécresse is struggling to take off in the polls — despite having had an initial boost last year when she was picked to be the French conservatives' first female presidential candidate.</p>
								<p>The fact that Pécresse has not held any major launch rallies like other candidates, owing to earlier concerns over soaring omicron infections, seems to have hurt her. </p>
								<p>She is stalling in popularity behind far-right leader Marine Le Pen and frontrunner President Emmanuel Macron, who has still not officially declared his candidacy. All potential candidates must do so by March 4.</p>
								<p>On Sunday in the Zenith Arena in Paris, Pécresse, tried to reverse that stall. To chants of "Valerie" and "We will win!" the head of the Paris region and former conservative minister brandished her credentials for France's top job to thousands of supporters.</p>
								<p>"Even if you fail, it means you've tried ... I'm this indomitable French woman. Nothing will stop me!" she said to cheering crowds.</p>
								<p>An experienced politician, Pécresse has been the French minister for higher education, for the budget and was a government spokesperson under former President Nicolas Sarkozy from 2007 to 2012.</p>
								<p>In the often tough-talking speech, she again backed a hard stance on immigration, apparently seeking backing from both conservatives and the far right. </p>
								<p>She said the symbol of France, Marianne, "was not veiled" and has said that people who entered the country illegally should be deported.</p>
								<p>On Sunday, she went even further in her rhetoric, defending the idea of building "walls" to seal off the borders of the 27-nation European Union.</p>
								<p>However, she also hit back at far-right politicians, saying they did not represent the country she wants to lead. </p>
								<p>"I embody, with you, order in the Republic. They are the disorder. I embody the force of the national unity. They are disunity. Against this extremism, chose a firm and fair hand", she said.</p>
								<p>A supporter of the EU, Pécresse left The Republicans party in 2019 amid leadership divisions after the party had a poor showing in EU elections. She rejoined the party this year.</p>
								<p>She also tried to cast herself as strong on families, promising a substantial increase in small pensions and pledging to slash inheritance taxes for many and hire an extra 25,000 caregivers. Pécresse said her first action as president would be to end France's 35-hour workweek so employees can work and earn more.</p>
								<p>If elected, Pécresse vowed again to break with the centrist policies of incumbent Macron, who is expected to seek a second term. She has also warned voters against backing far-right candidates, arguing that only the conservatives can unite the French people and ease political tensions in the country.</p>
								<p>===========================================================</p>
								<p>Clients are reminded: </p>
								<p>(i) to check the terms of their licence agreements for use of content outside news programming and that further advice and assistance can be obtained from the AP Archive on: Tel +44 (0) 20 7482 7482 Email: info@aparchive.com</p>
								<p>(ii) they should check with the applicable collecting society in their Territory regarding the clearance of any sound recording or performance included within the AP Television News service </p>
								<p>(iii) they have editorial responsibility for the use of all and any content included within the AP Television News service and for libel, privacy, compliance and third party rights applicable to their Territory.</p>
							</div>
						</html>
					</DataContent>
				</ContentItem>
			</NewsComponent>
		</NewsComponent>
	</NewsItem>
</NewsML>