<NewsML Version="1.2" xmlns="http://iptc.org/std/NewsML/2003-10-10/">
	<NewsEnvelope>
		<TransmissionId>urn:publicid:ap.org:111668</TransmissionId>
		<SentFrom>
			<Party FormalName="The Associated Press" />
		</SentFrom>
		<DateAndTime>20220213T214011</DateAndTime>
		<NewsService FormalName="ent_daily" />
	</NewsEnvelope>
	<NewsItem>
		<Identification>
			<NewsIdentifier>
				<ProviderId>www.ap.org</ProviderId>
				<DateId>20220213</DateId>
				<NewsItemId>28436c25-c626-4921-a61e-2fa5577d15cf.1</NewsItemId>
				<RevisionId PreviousRevision="0" Update="N">1</RevisionId>
				<PublicIdentifier>urn:newsml:www.ap.org:20220213:28436c25-c626-4921-a61e-2fa5577d15cf.1:1</PublicIdentifier>
			</NewsIdentifier>
			<Label>
				<LabelType FormalName="StoryNumber" />
				<LabelText>4365895</LabelText>
			</Label>
		</Identification>
		<NewsManagement>
			<NewsItemType FormalName="Video" />
			<FirstCreated>20220213T214011</FirstCreated>
			<ThisRevisionCreated>20220213T214011</ThisRevisionCreated>
			<Status FormalName="Usable" />
		</NewsManagement>
		<NewsComponent Essential="yes" EquivalentsList="yes">
			<Role FormalName="Main" />
			<BasisForChoice>MimeType/@FormalName</BasisForChoice>
			<NewsLines>
				<HeadLine>Boats lit up in Venice for first weekend of carnival</HeadLine>
				<DateLine>13 February 2022 - Venice</DateLine>
				<SlugLine>Italy Venice Carnival</SlugLine>
			</NewsLines>
			<AdministrativeMetadata />
			<NewsComponent>
				<Role FormalName="Script" />
				<ContentItem>
					<MimeType FormalName="application/xhtml+xml" />
					<DataContent>
						<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
							<div>
								<p></p>
								<p>SHOTLIST:</p>
								<p>RESTRICTION SUMMARY:</p>
								<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p> Venice - 13 February 2022</p>
								<p>++NIGHT SHOTS++</p>
								<p>1. Various of the water parade with traditional boats illuminated by coloured lights </p>
								<p>2. SOUNDBITE (Italian) Massimo Checchetto, art director of Venice Carnival: </p>
								<p>"This parade wants to send a message to the world, that Venice is alive, the Carnival is here and we hope to come back at full swing next year, but for the time being a little bit of taste of the Carnival. This is the meaning of this year's parade". </p>
								<p>3. The "pantegana", a boat with a giant water rat, leading the water parade </p>
								<p>4. SOUNDBITE (Italian) Massimo Checchetto, art director of Venice Carnival: </p>
								<p>"We decided recreate all the traditional characters of previous carnivals. We wanted to put all of them together toward the future, toward the next Carnival." </p>
								<p>5. Various of a performer dancing attached to a large white inflatable balloon </p>
								<p>6. Water parade </p>
								<p>7. Pan left from people gathered along a bank watching the show to the parade </p>
								<p>8. Close up the screen of a smartphone filming the parade </p>
								<p>9. Tilt down from the white inflatable balloon to the performer dancing attached to it  </p>
								<p>10. Wide of the water parade </p>
								<p>STORYLINE:</p>
								<p>Dozens of traditional boats illuminated by coloured lights and fires paraded to the sound of drums along the Grand Canal in Venice on Sunday evening in the first weekend of Carnival celebrations. </p>
								<p>The parade, led by the "pantegana", a boat with a giant water rat, had been announced at the last moment, to avoid drawing the sort of crowds of locals and tourists that gathered along the banks of the canal before the pandemic to watch the show. </p>
								<p>The festive procession, with performers wearing colourful, traditional costumes and masks, started from the Venice Casino and reached Punta della Dogana, the triangular area of Venice where the Grand Canal meets the Giudecca Canal, in the San Marco basin. </p>
								<p>A large white inflatable balloon, attached to one of the boats, hovered in the sky like a moon, with a performer attached to the cable dancing. </p>
								<p>According to the Carnival organisation, over 100,000 people attended the first two days, more than half of them foreign tourists. </p>
								<p>Venetians and tourists on Saturday swapped surgical masks for carnival masks and costumes, to mark the start of the famed carnival celebrations. </p>
								<p>Italian authorities revoked the obligation to wear masks outdoors on Friday and visitors were thronging Saint Mark's Square, enjoying the return of carnival, after the pandemic had previously shut the festival down. </p>
								<p>However, some of the most awaited attractions, such as the Flight of the Angel and the Venice Carnival Costume Competition, were cancelled this year. </p>
								<p>This year the Venice carnival, runs from February 12 to March 1, leading into Lent. </p>
								<p>===========================================================</p>
								<p>Clients are reminded: </p>
								<p>(i) to check the terms of their licence agreements for use of content outside news programming and that further advice and assistance can be obtained from the AP Archive on: Tel +44 (0) 20 7482 7482 Email: info@aparchive.com</p>
								<p>(ii) they should check with the applicable collecting society in their Territory regarding the clearance of any sound recording or performance included within the AP Television News service </p>
								<p>(iii) they have editorial responsibility for the use of all and any content included within the AP Television News service and for libel, privacy, compliance and third party rights applicable to their Territory.</p>
							</div>
						</html>
					</DataContent>
				</ContentItem>
			</NewsComponent>
		</NewsComponent>
	</NewsItem>
</NewsML>