<NewsML Version="1.2" xmlns="http://iptc.org/std/NewsML/2003-10-10/">
	<NewsEnvelope>
		<TransmissionId>urn:publicid:ap.org:111668</TransmissionId>
		<SentFrom>
			<Party FormalName="The Associated Press" />
		</SentFrom>
		<DateAndTime>20220214T021352</DateAndTime>
		<NewsService FormalName="horizons" />
	</NewsEnvelope>
	<NewsItem>
		<Identification>
			<NewsIdentifier>
				<ProviderId>www.ap.org</ProviderId>
				<DateId>20220214</DateId>
				<NewsItemId>a4b98173-4f1f-48b7-b9ea-4fc515cd3eda.1</NewsItemId>
				<RevisionId PreviousRevision="0" Update="N">1</RevisionId>
				<PublicIdentifier>urn:newsml:www.ap.org:20220214:a4b98173-4f1f-48b7-b9ea-4fc515cd3eda.1:1</PublicIdentifier>
			</NewsIdentifier>
			<Label>
				<LabelType FormalName="StoryNumber" />
				<LabelText>4365632</LabelText>
			</Label>
		</Identification>
		<NewsManagement>
			<NewsItemType FormalName="Video" />
			<FirstCreated>20220214T021352</FirstCreated>
			<ThisRevisionCreated>20220214T021352</ThisRevisionCreated>
			<Status FormalName="Usable" />
		</NewsManagement>
		<NewsComponent Essential="yes" EquivalentsList="yes">
			<Role FormalName="Main" />
			<BasisForChoice>MimeType/@FormalName</BasisForChoice>
			<NewsLines>
				<HeadLine>Southern churches merge for racial reconciliation </HeadLine>
				<DateLine>8 February 2022 - Charlotte/Kannapolis, North Carolina </DateLine>
				<SlugLine>HZ US Multi Racial Church</SlugLine>
			</NewsLines>
			<AdministrativeMetadata />
			<NewsComponent>
				<Role FormalName="Script" />
				<ContentItem>
					<MimeType FormalName="application/xhtml+xml" />
					<DataContent>
						<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
							<div>
								<p></p>
								<p>US MULTI RACIAL CHURCH</p>
								<p>SHOTLIST:</p>
								<p>SOURCE: ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p>RESTRICTION SUMMARY:</p>
								<p>LENGTH: 6:22</p>
								<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p>Kannapolis, North Carolina - 8 February 2022</p>
								<p>1. Refuge Church members Troy and April Savage walk towards church with their family</p>
								<p>2. The Refuge Church sign</p>
								<p>3. Various of Refuge Church  </p>
								<p>4. Troy and April Savage walking into church</p>
								<p>5. Various of Troy and April Savage with church members in lobby</p>
								<p>6. SOUNDBITE (English) Troy Savage, Refuge Church member: </p>
								<p>"It's been said that the most segregated hour in America is Sunday morning at 11. You know, and it's true. Because we work together, different races, different ethnicities, cultures, we work together every day, we have our different friends that we go, we hang out, social gatherings. And then on Sunday morning, we do this, and we go our separate ways."</p>
								<p>7. Various of Troy and April Savage praying in church</p>
								<p>8. SOUNDBITE (English) Troy Savage, Refuge Church member:  </p>
								<p>"I did not even go to a multi ethnic church until I was almost 30 years old. So all my experience was always the Black Church."</p>
								<p>9.  April Savage praying in church</p>
								<p>10. SOUNDBITE (English) April Savage, Refuge Church member: </p>
								<p>"I think for so long religion has separated us more than it has brought us together."</p>
								<p>11. Refuge Church interior </p>
								<p>12  Pastor Jay Stewart leading service</p>
								<p>13. Church member holding Bible </p>
								<p>14. Church members praying together</p>
								<p>15. Troy and April Savage holding hands</p>
								<p>16. Troy and April Savage praying in church</p>
								<p>17. SOUNDBITE (English) April Savage, Refuge Church member: </p>
								<p>"When we think about racial reconciliation, really our goals should be to do what Jesus wanted us to do."</p>
								<p>18. Church members worshipping together</p>
								<p>19. Derrick Hawkins co-pastor preaching</p>
								<p>20. Jonathan and Summer Daniel praying together </p>
								<p>21. SOUNDBITE (English) Jonathan Daniel, Refuge Church member:  </p>
								<p>"I believe overall, the average American does want unity. Are there racist people? Absolutely. And there's always going to be racist people. But I believe as a whole, America does want to see unity."</p>
								<p>22. Pan from worshippers to Derrick Hawkins, co-pastor, preaching</p>
								<p>23. SOUNDBITE (English) Jonathan Daniel, Refuge Church member:</p>
								<p>"I think it is a scriptural thing, I mean Psalm 133 says that unity is where the Lord commands blessing."</p>
								<p>24. Church members praying together</p>
								<p>25. SOUNDBITE (English) Jonathan Daniel, Refuge Church member:</p>
								<p>"I didn't get any push back from any of my friends, everyone I've talked to thought this was a really good thing."</p>
								<p>26. Various of church members praying together</p>
								<p>27. SOUNDBITE (English) April Savage, Refuge Church member:  </p>
								<p>"Now, I'll tell you, I'll be honest with you, not everybody understands it. Some people, they may not say it out of their mouth, but they feel like, oh, like you abandoned your people, Because you're going to this, predominantly, you know, white ministry, or however you want to classify it. But we choose to not look at it that way. We choose to look at it as this is the kingdom of God, and it's the kingdom that brings us together, we all believe the same."</p>
								<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p>Charlotte, North Carolina - 8 February 2022</p>
								<p>28. Exterior Greater Bethel AME Church in Charlotte, North Carolina</p>
								<p>29. Pan to Rev. Abdul Knox inside church</p>
								<p>30. SOUNDBITE (English) Rev. Abdul Knox, Greater Bethel Church: </p>
								<p>"We really have to do what's best for our family, and if it's best for our family to worship in, and it might sound confusing, but if it's better for our family to worship in an interracial setup, that's great. But as a pastor, to another interracial pastor, don't forget and don't leave out and don't neglect, the struggle, the Black struggle, we have that we have to include that. That's a part of our faith formation."</p>
								<p>ASSOCIATED PRESS</p>
								<p>Kannapolis, North Carolina - 8 February 2022</p>
								<p>31. Derrick Hawkins preaching</p>
								<p>32. Church members praying together</p>
								<p>33. SOUNDBITE (English) Rev. Derrick Hawkins, Refuge Church:</p>
								<p>"You know, faith in the African American community has always been all we had. And so we lean to what I knew to do is to always resolve in seeking the Spirit of God for unity, we can't do it in our own ability. There's never been a policy created, any speech that's able to unite. It's only the power in the presence of God that unites us."</p>
								<p>34. Church members attempting to heal each other through prayer </p>
								<p>35. Pastor Jay Stewart leading service </p>
								<p>36. SOUNDBITE (English) Rev. Jay Stewart, The Refuge Church: </p>
								<p>"And for us, a part of our purpose is: be a demonstration of unity, be a demonstration of racial reconciliation in a nation that has been so divided for way too long. And we get the privilege of walking out this purpose."</p>
								<p>37. Church members praying together</p>
								<p>38. April Savage hugs a fellow church member</p>
								<p>LEADIN:</p>
								<p>More than five years ago, Refuge Church, a formerly white congregation in North Carolina, merged with an African American church.</p>
								<p>The move was an effort to be an example of unity and racial reconciliation in the American South. </p>
								<p>STORYLINE:</p>
								<p>April and Troy Savage and their two children are part of an experiment at the Refuge Church in Kannapolis, North Carolina. </p>
								<p>This formerly predominantly white congregation merged with an African American church in an attempt to use religion as a vehicle for racial reconciliation in the south.</p>
								<p>"It's been said that the most segregated hour in America is Sunday morning at 11," says Troy Savage. </p>
								<p>"Because we work together, different races, different ethnicities, cultures, we work together every day, we have our different friends that we go, we hang out, social gatherings. And then on Sunday morning... we go our separate ways."</p>
								<p>Savage did not go to a multi-racial church until he was almost 30 years old. </p>
								<p>"I think for so long religion has separated us more than it has brought us together," says his wife April Savage. </p>
								<p>And she believes that racial reckoning means doing what Jesus would want them to do.</p>
								<p>Jonathan and Summer Daniel and their four children joined the church six years ago, just before the merger with the African American Church. </p>
								<p>"I believe overall, the average American does want unity," says Daniel. </p>
								<p>"Are there racist people? Absolutely. And there's always going to be racist people. But I believe as a whole, America does want to see unity." </p>
								<p>Daniel says that everyone he talked to thought that the joining of the churches was a really good thing.</p>
								<p>However, transition to this Church was difficult for the Savage family. </p>
								<p>April says not everyone she's encountered understands it</p>
								<p>"Some people, they may not say it out of their mouth, but they feel like, oh, like you abandoned your people, Because you're going through this, predominantly, you know, white ministry, or however you want to classify it," she says.</p>
								<p>"But we choose to not look at it that way. We choose to look at it as this is the kingdom of God, and it's the kingdom that brings us together, we all believe the same."</p>
								<p>But some ministers urge caution.</p>
								<p>Rev. Abdul Knox of Greater Bethel Church in Charlotte, North Carolina, says the experiences of Black people must not be forgotten in multi racial churches.</p>
								<p>"If it's better for our family to worship in an interracial setup, that's great," he says. </p>
								<p>"But as a pastor, to another interracial pastor, don't forget and don't leave out and don't neglect, the struggle, the Black struggle, we have that we have to include that. That's a part of our faith formation."</p>
								<p>Derrick Hawkins was the lead pastor at the African American church and helped spearhead the merger with the Refuge Church.</p>
								<p>"Faith in the African American community has always been all we had," he says. </p>
								<p>"And so we lean to what I knew to do is to always resolve in seeking the Spirit of God for unity, we can't do it in our own ability. There's never been a policy created, any speech that's able to unite. It's only the power in the presence of God that unites us."</p>
								<p>Jay Stewart is the Lead Pastor at the Refuge Church and worked with Derrick Hawkins to unite their churches.</p>
								<p>"For us, a part of our purpose is be a demonstration of unity, be a demonstration of racial reconciliation in a nation that has been so divided for way too long," says Stewart. </p>
								<p>"And we get the privilege of walking out this purpose."</p>
								<p>The service blends Christian Bible Study, Evangelical Healing, and Speaking in Tongues.  </p>
								<p>Although the church is still a work in progress, to the Savage and Daniel families, it is a real commitment to racial harmony.</p>
								<p>___</p>
								<p>Associated Press religion coverage receives support from the Lilly Endowment through the Religion News Foundation. The AP is solely responsible for this content.</p>
								<p>====</p>
								<p>Clients are reminded: </p>
								<p>(i) to check the terms of their licence agreements for use of content outside news programming and that further advice and assistance can be obtained from the AP Archive on: Tel +44 (0) 20 7482 7482 Email: info@aparchive.com. </p>
								<p>(ii) they should check with the applicable collecting society in their Territory regarding the clearance of any sound recording or performance included within the AP Television News service </p>
								<p>(iii) they have editorial responsibility for the use of all and any content included within the AP Television News service and for libel, privacy, compliance and third party rights applicable to their Territory.</p>
							</div>
						</html>
					</DataContent>
				</ContentItem>
			</NewsComponent>
		</NewsComponent>
	</NewsItem>
</NewsML>